LIST OF COURT MAIDS
‪（《宫女出宫账簿》）
"Year of Imjin."
‪“壬辰年”
And your stance must be wider.
‪步幅要往这边再跨大一点
Who are you?
‪你是谁？
It's me, Hyun.
‪是我 显
Hyun?
‪显？
YANG SUN-JI
‪（梁纯知）
DEOK-HUI
‪（德熙）
DAM-I
‪（垣）
She left due to an illness?
‪她因病出了宫？
Does the record specify the illness?
‪有记录是罹患了什么病吗？
This is all we have on a girl named Dam-i.
‪关于垣的记录就只有这些了
Usually, the illness is specified.
‪通常会依据病症另外做个简略的记录
But for some reason, there is no record of it.
‪但不晓得为何没有关于她的任何记录
If I may, can I ask why you wish to know?
‪不过您为何要问这个？
Never mind.
‪没什么
DAM-I
‪（垣）
The Crown Prince had the book I gave to the girl.
‪我送给她的书在邸下手上
The Crown Prince?
‪邸下？
No one can match his anti-climactic ways.
‪没人比他更无聊了
Was that the reason, Your Royal Highness?
‪所以你才会那样吗？邸下
I thought it was a dream.
‪我还以为那是个梦
However…
‪然而…
it wasn't…
‪那个…
STAY, LONGING
‪（停 恋）
…a dream.
‪却不是梦
I will believe you if you say the feelings were momentary.
‪若您说那是一时被动摇了 ‪我会相信您的
But…
‪但是
it wasn't for me.
‪我并非如此
It wasn't admiration from a subject.
‪我不是以臣子之心相待
I thought it was my loyalty to you.
‪我曾以为自己是出于忠心
But it was affection.
‪结果却是恋慕之情
I have a deep affection for you, Your Royal Highness.
‪我爱慕着您 邸下
Although you're a man and the Crown Prince of this nation,
‪即便您是男儿身 ‪又贵为这个国家的王储
I…
‪我还是…
love you.
‪爱慕着您
Royal Tutor Jung.
‪郑司书
We…
‪我们是
cannot be together.
‪无法厮守的关系
I am the Crown Prince of this nation,
‪我是这个国家的世子
and you are my subject.
‪你则是我的臣子
I will endure it.
‪我会承受的
Whatever people say… No.
‪无论世人如何对我指指点点…不
Whatever you say,
‪无论邸下对我说什么
I will…
‪我都会
endure it all.
‪一肩扛下来
I don't…
‪我…
feel the same way.
‪跟你不一样
Whatever you think you felt from me, I ask you to please…
‪不管我那天是出于何种情感
forget about that night.
‪忘了那件事
-Your Royal Highness. -We never…
‪-邸下 ‪-你今日的这番话
had this conversation.
‪我就当作没听见
EPISODE 10
‪第 10 集
JASEONDANG
‪（资善堂）
Perhaps,
‪倒不如
it might have been better if we had never met again.
‪打从一开始就不要重逢还比较好
If we hadn't,
‪那么我们
we wouldn't have had to be in such pain like this.
‪就不会如此心痛了
YEON-SEON
‪（莲膳）
Ji-un!
‪大哥！
You should come on out!
‪出来一下
Hurry!
‪快啊！
What is it?
‪怎么了？
What…
‪那个…
What brings you here?
‪您怎么会来这里？
You're a late riser.
‪你起得太晚了
Can't you see that the sun has fully risen in the sky?
‪现在都日正当头了
What do you mean His Royal Highness isn't at the palace?
‪邸下不在宫中？
He must know that the Queen Dowager is expecting to see him this afternoon.
‪她不可能忘了下午要到大妃殿一趟啊
He does know. He is aware,
‪她记得 不过…
but something urgent came up.
‪她突然有急事…
How could you let this happen?
‪你到底是怎么服侍邸下的？
Where did His Royal Highness go?
‪邸下去哪里了？
I must go now and escort him back to the palace.
‪我现在立刻就追上去请邸下回来
Naturally, he didn't have a destination.
‪那不可能会有特定的目的地啊
His bodyguard went with him.
‪邸下的护卫武士也有随行
So you don't have to worry.
‪你不要太担心
And I told the bodyguard, Kim Ga-on,
‪我已经嘱咐金佳稳
to stay very close to the Crown Prince.
‪要随侍在邸下身侧
He does everything I ask of him now.
‪他最近可是对我言听计从
You cannot enter the Crown Prince's quarters today.
‪你今天绝对不能进东宫殿
Better yet. You should go home for the day.
‪不 你干脆现在就出宫
You went to the market with the Crown Prince today.
‪你今天随着邸下去了市集
Do you understand?
‪明白了吗？
If Court Lady Kim sees you, you and I are dead meat.
‪你被金尚宫娘娘发现的话 ‪我们俩就完蛋了
What is this about?
‪那是什么意思？
Lord Jaeun.
‪者隐君大监
Did the Crown Prince leave the palace?
‪邸下出宫了吗？
Well, it's not what you think.
‪不是那样的…
Enjoy.
‪请慢用
Aren't you going to eat?
‪你不吃吗？
I will.
‪好
Right. Hold on.
‪对喔 等等
It's ready now.
‪可以吃了
But…
‪话说
what really brings you here?
‪您来找我是为了什么事？
I doubt you came out for a mere bowl of soup.
‪您应该不会只为了一碗汤饭而出宫
I did.
‪你说得没错
I couldn't stop thinking about this soup.
‪我经常想起这里的汤饭
Do you mean that?
‪您是说真的吗？
The soup will get cold. We should eat now.
‪汤饭要凉了 快吃吧
A bag of that, please.
‪请给我一包这个
Can you buy this for me?
‪你买给我吃吧
Sure.
‪好的
I see. He's grinning from ear to ear.
‪这嬉皮笑脸的样子
He looks just like you.
‪就跟你如出一辙
Is that so?
‪是这样吗？
How is your hat today?
‪今天你纱帽的状况如何？
I'm glad to hear that.
‪那就好
The flowers have bloomed beautifully.
‪花开得很漂亮
Yes, indeed.
‪就是说啊
All right. Does anyone want to try it?
‪来 有人想要挑战吗？
Who wants to try?
‪谁想来挑战？
-Your Royal Highness. -Hold on!
‪-邸下 ‪-等等 唉唷
Come on, everyone. Let's give him a round of applause!
‪大家别愣着 快给他一个掌声
-One, two, three! -Two, three!
‪-一 二 三 ‪-二 三
Let's give it up for him!
‪大家快鼓掌
Are you all right?
‪你还好吗？
Everyone, give him a round of applause!
‪再给他一个掌声！来
Here I go!
‪-我要开始了 ‪-小心
I'm good.
‪要飞起来了
Would you like to try it?
‪您想试试看吗？
Pardon?
‪什么？
Gosh. That's only for women.
‪那是给女子玩的
Over here! Someone wants to try out the swing.
‪不好意思 这里有人想荡秋千
What are you doing?
‪你在做什么？
Who says it's only for women?
‪谁说那只能给女子玩？
A fun activity belongs to everyone.
‪好东西就要一起尽兴啊
My lord, try it. It's very fun.
‪书生 你试试看 很有趣
-Come on. -Wait. No. I…
‪我…
Try it.
‪试试看嘛
He's good.
‪好厉害
Goodness. I can't believe I got to ride a swing thanks to you.
‪真不敢相信我有生之年 ‪居然会托你的福荡了秋千
What a strange experience.
‪真是出乎意料
Thanks to you, I got to use up my energy today.
‪我才是托邸下的福 ‪久违地展现了我的力量
It really was strange.
‪确实很出乎意料
Must you really have the last word just because we're outside the palace?
‪怎么到了宫外 ‪你就一句话都不肯输？
Gosh. How could I do that? That's a misunderstanding.
‪唉唷 怎么会呢？邸下
Look.
‪您看
I see a big bird over the mountain. Over there.
‪那边有只大鸟飞过了山头…
We should stay under the roof over there for now.
‪邸下 我们先到那边的屋檐下避雨吧
Okay.
‪好
Your robe is all wet.
‪您的衣服都湿透了 该怎么办？
You shouldn't catch a cold.
‪染上风寒就糟糕了
I can shake off the rain myself.
‪我自己来
Your Royal Highness, please tell me
‪现在请您告诉我吧 邸下
the real reason why
‪您今天来找我的
you came to visit me today.
‪真正目的是什么
Sometimes, I think about how it would be to live a normal life like them.
‪有时候我也会想若能过着 ‪跟他们一样的生活会是如何
Laughing as they please
‪能尽情地欢笑
and crying their hearts out whenever they want to.
‪想哭的时候
It's impossible to be true to myself
‪因为身在宫中 我连面对自己
when I'm in the palace.
‪都无法坦诚
I've lived my whole life competing.
‪我毕生都在竞争中求生存
I lived to meet expectations.
‪为了迎合他人的期待而活
And I will
‪往后
have to keep doing so in the future.
‪我也一样会过着相同的日子吧
People may envy me for being the Crown Prince.
‪世人可能会羡慕我世子的身份
But I envy the people out here.
‪但我却羡慕着这里的百姓
They enjoy life to their heart's content…
‪他们不必顾虑别人的目光
without having to worry about what others think of them.
‪只要尽情地享受幸福就好
Why don't you do the same, Your Royal Highness?
‪您就这么做吧 邸下
You can laugh like today
‪像今天一样欢笑
and cry at times too…
‪偶尔落泪也不要紧
at least with me.
‪在我面前时就这么做吧
Thank you for everything.
‪谢谢你
Thanks to you,
‪多亏你
I was happy even if it was just for one day.
‪我才能够度过这么幸福的一天
Your Royal Highness…
‪邸下
I found a better position for you.
‪我替你安排了更好的官职
I believe taking that position
‪你调职到那边
will be a good opportunity for you.
‪对你来说也是个绝佳的机会
Are you…
‪您是在
ordering me to leave?
‪命令我离开吗？
You can criticize me for being selfish.
‪你可以骂我自私
I will…
‪因为我
soon get married
‪很快就要举行嘉礼
and have a wife.
‪迎娶世子嫔
This is…
‪这就是
my answer…
‪我对你的表白
to your feelings for me.
‪所作出的答复
It must have been a tough day.
‪你似乎遇上了让你难受的事
Hyun.
‪王兄
There are days like this.
‪人难免会遇上那种日子
I know…
‪我今天
because today has been tough for me too.
‪也正逢那种日子呢
I suspect you'd have more use for it.
‪比起我 王兄更需要这个吧
You should give it to the lady that steals your heart.
‪你才该把这送给你日后爱慕的女子
Did you just arrive at the palace?
‪你刚进宫啊
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‪是的 邸下
You were caught in the rain yesterday. Are you all right?
‪您昨日淋了雨 没什么大碍吧？
Yes. I'm all right.
‪对 我当然没事
Are you headed somewhere?
‪您好像要前往某处
I must meet with my father to talk about the royal marriage.
‪我要跟我父王商讨国婚事宜
I see.
‪这样啊
Let's go.
‪走吧
I would like to get married.
‪孩儿想举行嘉礼
I thought we already discussed this.
‪那件事不是早有定论了吗？
Your Majesty, the refreshments are ready.
‪殿下 茶点已备好
I heard you enjoy chrysanthemum tea around this time of the year.
‪听说你到这种时候就特别喜爱菊花茶
Your mother also liked chrysanthemum tea.
‪嫔宫也很喜欢菊花茶
But…
‪但是我
I had never brewed tea for her.
‪却不曾像这样替她沏过一壶茶
Do you know why I am against your marriage?
‪你知道我为何会反对世子的嘉礼吗？
It must be because you don't think I am ready
‪因为孩儿在父王眼中
to take the next step.
‪还不甚成熟
I got married when I was your age.
‪我也是在你这个年纪举行嘉礼的
I made a family at a young age.
‪我在年幼时就建立了家庭
So I didn't know
‪所以并不晓得
how precious it was or how to protect it.
‪其珍贵之处与守护它的方法
So…
‪因此我
I failed…
‪无法好好地
to protect my family.
‪守护我的家庭
But…
‪我不想…
I didn't want you to make the same mistake.
‪让你也建立那种不成熟的家庭
Your grandmother is right
‪若将你当成世子
if I only consider your duty as the Crown Prince.
‪我理应遵从大妃的意思
But you are also my son,
‪但若将你当成儿子
so I wanted to buy you some time.
‪我就想再多给你一点时间
Do you truly want to get married now?
‪你真的想举行嘉礼吗？
Yes.
‪是的
I want to get married.
‪孩儿想举行嘉礼
The royal marriage of the Crown Prince
‪世子的国婚
is not the same as the marriage of a nobleman.
‪并不若一介士大夫的婚事
It's an important occasion where the fate of Joseon lies.
‪那是攸关朝鲜命运的国家大事
I'm sure you understand
‪你晓得
what this means.
‪我这番话的意思吧？
I examined the body three times so far,
‪我已进行了三次尸检
but I didn't find anything unusual.
‪并未发现异常之处
What about the right shoulder fracture you mentioned before?
‪你那时提到的右肩骨折呢？
The height of the fall was over five cheok.
‪其坠落的高度超过五尺
So it must be from the fall after the arrow hit him.
‪那应该是他中箭后坠落时所受的伤
Commander Yoon, a soldier from one of the Five Central Armies asks for you.
‪内禁卫长大人 有个义兴卫士兵求见
I heard we already took statements
‪关于讲武场之案
from everyone involved with the royal hunting.
‪我已经收到所有相关人士的供词
Well, I was on extended sick leave due to a medical condition.
‪那是因为小的身体不适 ‪休了很长的一段病假
So I must have been omitted from the list for testimonies.
‪所以才没被列入陈述名单之中
All right. What is it that you want to tell me?
‪好 你想禀报什么？
The man that was considered the suspect did not have the capacity to kill.
‪那个被指认的犯人 ‪并没有足够的胆量杀人
I'm one of the people who are happy to see him dead,
‪虽然他死了 我也同样感到很痛快
but someone like him couldn't have tried to kill the Crown Prince.
‪但他不太可能去刺杀世子邸下
It doesn't make sense.
‪这不管怎么想都令人费解
Shoot.
‪射箭
His shoulder was injured?
‪他的肩膀受伤了？
Three days before we got selected,
‪在被选为讲武场先遣部队的三天前
he got into a fight when we were drinking together.
‪他跟和我同席喝酒的人起了争执
He injured his right shoulder then. So he couldn't even lift a bow.
‪当时他们大打出手 ‪他的右肩受到重伤
But he shot at the Crown Prince?
‪但是他却对邸下放冷箭？
That didn't sit well with me.
‪这一点让小的十分在意
Shoot.
‪射箭
Next.
‪下一组
Get ready.
‪准备
Shoot.
‪射箭
-Who are you?
‪-来者何人？
Commander Yoon. What brings you here?
‪内禁卫长大人 你怎么会来这里？
Where is Kim Ga-on?
‪金佳稳在哪里？
He headed to the King's quarters a while ago to see His Majesty.
‪他稍早去大殿觐见殿下
What did you say? The King's quarters?
‪你说什么？大殿？
I'm Kim Ga-on.
‪臣是金佳稳
Ask him.
‪传话给殿下
Your Majesty, Commander Yoon asks for an audience.
‪殿下 内禁卫长请求觐见
Let him in.
‪让他进来
What brings you here at this late hour?
‪这么晚了你有什么事？
I have something to report.
‪臣有事要禀报
But I will wait outside.
‪我到外面等候
All right. Wait a moment.
‪好 你稍待片刻
I heard that you are the Crown Prince's bodyguard.
‪寡人听说你负责世子的护卫
So how is it? Are you having any trouble?
‪说说看 有没有什么难处？
No, Your Majesty.
‪没有 殿下
I had noticed a tally on your sword
‪你交予尚膳保管的那把剑
you handed over to my eunuch.
‪似乎挂有符节
Was it from your betrothed?
‪那是你的情人赠予的吗？
TALLY: MADE OF STONE, BAMBOO, OR JADE, SPLIT IN HALF AND USED FOR IDENTIFICATION
‪（以石、竹及玉制成 ‪以示身份的信物）
It's a keepsake from my late father.
‪那是臣已逝之父的遗物
I see.
‪好
Continue to do your utmost to guard the Crown Prince.
‪往后你也要竭尽全力护卫世子
There was a murder in the Ministry of War just now.
‪稍早在兵曹的官厅里发生了凶杀案
How could there be a murder in one of our six ministries?
‪怎么会在六曹的官厅中发生这种事？
Was the culprit caught?
‪犯人抓到了吗？
The man who just left, Kim Ga-on.
‪方才离开的金佳稳
There's something suspicious about him.
‪他的行踪很可疑
What do you mean?
‪那是什么意思？
So His Majesty finally gave his blessing for the royal marriage?
‪殿下终于同意着手进行拣择了？
This will impact the fate of our nation.
‪此事关乎一国的国本
He knew that the Crown Prince had to fulfill his duty soon.
‪殿下总不能一直事不关己
Did he say anything else?
‪殿下没有其他旨意吗？
The selected lady
‪世子嫔的拣择
will be the future queen of Joseon.
‪是要选出朝鲜未来国母的场合
As an elder of the royal family,
‪本宫身为王室的长辈
I will choose the wisest and most benevolent lady.
‪将会挑出最为明智又贤慧的人选
Do not worry.
‪请不必担心
Of course. I expect nothing less.
‪这是当然
That is why I would like to make a suitable recommendation.
‪因此臣想举荐合适的人选
Someone who will be helpful
‪那是个能对大妃娘娘与臣
to Your Highness, the Crown Prince, and me
‪以及世子邸下的前途
in our future endeavors.
‪有所助益的人选
-How pretty. Where did you get it? -You think so?
‪这块绸缎好美 你是在哪买的？
-My father bought me this. -Really?
‪这是我爹买给我的
-It looks like mine. -Really? Look at this.
‪-这看起来好像我的 ‪-真的吗？你看这个
You don't want to be in the selection process?
‪你要我别上呈拣择单？
I'm not ready to participate in the selection yet.
‪我还没做好参加拣择的心理准备
This isn't about whether you are ready or not.
‪现在重要的不是你是否准备好了
This is for our nation.
‪这是国家大事
I heard that
‪我听说世子嫔的拣择
they already have someone in mind for such selections.
‪原本私下就会有内定的人选
So no one will notice
‪因此只有我一个没被列入闺女单中
if I don't participate in the process.
‪也无人会在意
And women who participate three times
‪更何况进入三拣择之人
will have to remain chaste for the rest of their lives.
‪毕生都得守住贞节
I do not wish to lead such a life.
‪我不想过着那种生活
So please do not put my name in the process.
‪因此求你婉拒上呈拣择单 爹
If that's the law, you must follow it.
‪若那是国法 你就理应遵从
Don't make me a disloyal subject now.
‪别让我这个爹变成不忠之臣
-So-eun. -Yes?
‪-素恩 ‪-嗯？
This is just for your eyes. Come on.
‪这只给你看 快看啊
What's this?
‪这是什么？
The questions for the first round of the selection process.
‪听说这是今天初拣择会出的题目
I want to be chosen, but I shouldn't keep this from you either.
‪不管怎么说 我也不该隐瞒你这个啊
-I'm okay. Put this away. -Are you sure?
‪-我没关系 你快收回去 ‪-你真的不看？
Please follow me.
‪请随小的走
-Let's go. -Okay.
‪-走吧 ‪-嗯
I'm Jeong-hui, the eldest daughter of Deputy Magistrate Moon Jeong-hak
‪我是汉城府庶尹文廷鹤长女
at Hanseong Magistracy.
‪瀞伊
I'm So-eun, the eldest daughter of Shin Yeong-su,
‪我是吏曹判书辛莹秀长女
the Minister of Personnel.
‪素恩
I'm Ha-gyeong,
‪我是兵曹判书
the second-eldest daughter of No Hak-su, the Minister of War.
‪卢学修的次女贺庆
I'm Yeon-hui, the second-eldest daughter
‪我是弘文馆大提学
of Han Gyu-seong, the director at the Office of Royal Decrees.
‪韩圭诚的次女燕颐
A lord gave a test to three women.
‪某个大监要求他府中的三名女子
The test required them to last a month with just half a bag of rice.
‪展开仅用半袋米撑过一个月的试炼
One woman ate all the rice and when she ran out,
‪其中一个把米全数吃光后
she gave up on the test.
‪便弃权
And another woman ate the rice little by little,
‪另一个则是每次只吃一点
but she gave up as she was hungry.
‪最终因为饥肠辘辘而弃权
And the third woman lasted a month without having to eat the rice
‪第三个女子完全没吃分来的米
she was given.
‪却撑过了一个月
What did the third woman do?
‪她是怎么做到的？
She made rice cakes with the rice and sold them.
‪她利用那些米做成年糕来卖
She then bought more rice with that money.
‪再用那笔钱购入更多的米
That is correct.
‪答对了
Then do you think what she did was fair?
‪那你认为那名闺秀的行为是否得当？
Don't you think she cheated?
‪这难道不算使出不正当的手段吗？
Well…
‪那个…
Were there any rules that forbade her from doing so?
‪请问那个试炼中有其他规定吗？
No.
‪没有
Then she didn't cheat.
‪那么她就不算是使用了不正当的手段
In order to pass the test,
‪为了通过试炼
she put her skills in making rice cakes into good use
‪她充分发挥自身的能力做出年糕
and did her best.
‪全力以赴
How could that be considered cheating?
‪又何错之有呢？
You are So-eun, the daughter of the Minister of Personnel?
‪你是吏判之女
Yes, Your Highness.
‪是的
Do you mean to tell me you want my daughter to be the princess?
‪您的意思是打算 ‪让臣的女儿成为世子嫔吗？
When you first started working for me,
‪你还记得你刚出仕时
do you remember what you told me?
‪对寡人说过的话吗？
You said you would become a subject who would keep the royal court grounded
‪你说你不会倾向任何一方 ‪也不会权衡利弊得失
without being swayed by any biases or personal interests.
‪而会成为掌握朝廷核心 ‪并值得寡人信赖的臣子的
That is what you said.
‪那番话
I do remember, Your Majesty.
‪臣当然记得 殿下
My goal still hasn't changed.
‪现下臣的想法依然没变
-But-- -Now is the time…
‪-然而… ‪-此刻就是
that I need you to show me you meant what you said.
‪你兑现那番话的时候了
Oh, these.
‪这些啊？
He spared me a few.
‪这是公子分送给我的
My father hasn't come home from his post at the Ministry of Personnel.
‪我父亲因吏曹公务缠身尚未退朝
I'm aware.
‪我知道
I didn't come here to see your father. I came to see you.
‪我要找的人不是吏判大监 而是你
Me? Why?
‪您找我有何贵干？
Our bond seems stronger than I expected.
‪我们的缘分挺深的呢
Had I known that we would meet again,
‪当初若是知道日后会重逢
I wouldn't have lied about my identity that day.
‪那时就该告诉你我的真实身份
I apologize if you are surprised.
‪若是吓到你 我很抱歉
No, Your Royal Highness.
‪请别这么说
Please forgive me if I offended you in any way.
‪小女子当时若有失礼之处 ‪才要请您海涵
Your Royal Highness.
‪邸下
Just like your father's character,
‪如同吏判大监的性情
I can feel a sense of grace and honesty from this house.
‪这个家也同样显得淡雅方正
It's a cool day.
‪天气很凉爽
Would you like to accompany me for a walk?
‪你愿意陪我一块去散散步吗？
When you were ten, what kind of husband
‪你十岁的时候在这里
did you dream of from under this tree?
‪所描绘的夫君是什么模样？
Pardon?
‪什么？
When I was ten and standing under a pine tree in the backyard
‪站在宫廷后苑某棵松树下
at the palace…
‪十岁的我描绘的是
I dreamed of someone brave who would come to me
‪即便走向我的路布满荆棘
even if the path was long and full of thorns and bumps.
‪对方都能勇敢地披荆斩棘
I dreamed of someone
‪是一个十分美丽
upright and strong.
‪又强悍的人
The Minister of Personnel will help you.
‪吏判会助你一臂之力
Having him on your side will be
‪如此一来 他将会成为你日后
very helpful in your future.
‪莫大的助力
I'm here to ask you
‪我是来此
if you would be so kind as to walk that path.
‪询问你是否愿意跟我一同走上那条路
It will most likely be,
‪有力的内定人选
either Minister Shin's or Minister No's daughter.
‪应该就是吏判和兵判府上的闺秀吧
Then do you want to make a bet?
‪那我们来打个赌吧
I will bet on Minister No's daughter.
‪我赌兵判家的闺秀
Minister Shin is the symbol of integrity and the leader of Confucian scholars.
‪清廉刚正的儒生之首吏判大监
Lord Sangheon will never approve of him.
‪绝不可能受到尚宪君的青睐
Sure. Then I will bet on Minister Shin's daughter.
‪好 那我赌吏判大监家的闺秀
Do you think His Majesty will not object to accepting Minister No's daughter
‪众所皆知 兵判是隶属尚宪君的人马 ‪你认为主上殿下
Don't you agree, Royal Tutor Jung?
‪你说是不是啊？司书大人
Royal Tutor Jung!
‪郑司书！
Is it true?
‪那是真的吗？
Did the Crown Prince truly recommend giving you a promotion?
‪邸下推荐你调至更好的职位？
Is it true? So where are you getting transferred to?
‪是吗？所以你要调去哪里？
Is it the Office of the Censor General? Or the Office of the Inspector General?
‪是司谏院？还是司宪府？
Where is your next post?
‪到底是哪里？
That's not true.
‪没那回事
Come on. Don't keep things from me. Just tell me.
‪你不要这样 跟我说嘛
I'm not that petty. You know that. Right?
‪我又不是那种度量狭小的人
So which one is it?
‪所以是哪里？
Is it a big promotion?
‪是很大的官吗？
I'm sorry, but I'll head out a bit early today.
‪不好意思 我今天就先告退了
Don't be like that, Royal Tutor Jung. Just tell me. Royal Tutor Jung!
‪你别这样嘛 郑司书
Is he looking down on me because he's getting a promotion?
‪他现在因为要升官了 ‪就不把我放在眼里吗？
Gosh. My blood pressure is rising.
‪天啊 我的后脑勺…
Royal Scholar Yang!
‪唉唷
Royal Scholar Yang.
‪辅德大人
I'm not sure
‪小女子
if I will meet the expectations.
‪没有自信能胜任世子嫔
This is very sudden too.
‪而且这个请求也很突然
Do you
‪请问
have feelings for someone else?
‪你的心里是否另有意中人了？
Please forgive me.
‪小女子惶恐
As I came all the way here,
‪既然我都来到这里了
I don't think I can give up that easily.
‪就表示我无法轻言放弃
We'll meet again soon.
‪不久后再见吧
Why are you here at this hour?
‪这个时间您怎么会在这里？
I just left Minister Shin's house.
‪我刚去吏判府上拜访
The woman you were with the other day
‪上次跟你同行的女子
was Minister Shin's daughter.
‪原来是吏判家的闺秀
I asked her to be my wife…
‪我是去请她当世子嫔的
despite the fact that I knew that she had crossed paths with you.
‪即便知道她跟你有交情
I see.
‪是这样啊
Did you give some thought to the offer…
‪我之前提议的那件事
I made the other day?
‪你考虑过了吗？
If you want, I can recommend a better position.
‪若是你愿意 ‪我能推荐你担任更好的官职
When I see you…
‪当我见到邸下…
I want to talk with you.
‪就想跟您当面谈谈
And that desire gets stronger on days when I see you unexpectedly
‪像这样突然偶遇
like this.
‪这种念头就更强烈了
Offering another position
‪将我调离现在的职位
sounds like you're asking me to leave the palace.
‪对我而言就形同要撵我出宫一样
Is that truly what you want me to do?
‪您真的希望我那么做吗？
-If it's not-- -It was also…
‪-倘若并非如此… ‪-那也是我…
hard for me to tell you such things.
‪好不容易才向你吐露的心声
I thought you of all people would understand me.
‪我认为若是你肯定能理解我的用意
I guess I was wrong.
‪原来是我误解了
I understand now.
‪我现在知道了
The flowers have bloomed beautifully.
‪花开得很漂亮
Your lecture isn't today.
‪今日的书筵应该不是由你来上啊
I asked Royal Tutor Park to switch our lectures just for today.
‪我拜托文学让我调到今天
Then there won't be a lecture today.
‪今日的书筵就取消吧
You said…
‪您不是说
you wanted my answer.
‪想听臣的回复吗？
I will give you an answer afterward
‪等书筵结束 臣就会答复您
because this will be
‪今日将会是邸下和臣
our last lecture together.
‪最后一次的书筵
It means, "One can place the trees evenly,
‪即便木材均匀地摆放
but the drier parts of the trees will burn first."
‪火依旧会从干燥之处烧起
"One can flatten the ground,
‪即便是平地
but the water will spread to the humid side."
‪水依旧会流向潮湿之处
"Similar trees will grow together
‪相同品种的草木会群生
just like animals of a similar species will band together."
‪禽兽也是相同的物种会群居
"All things are bound to find their own."
‪万物皆是物以类聚
"Therefore, there must be a target board
‪因此
I will be your tutor starting from today. I am Royal Tutor Jung Ji-un.
‪臣是从今日起 ‪将负责邸下书筵的司书郑至韵
Then the lotus seed will bloom into a flower soon.
‪那么那些莲子应该很快就会开花了
I look forward to working for you until then, Your Royal Highness.
‪在那之前请多指教 邸下
to answer that question.
‪由我来回答你
Like the good rain that falls when most needed,
‪就如同一场及时雨
I will be someone who you can count on.
‪我也会在邸下有难时及时出手相救
Just like you were to me when I needed you the most.
‪就像邸下对我那般
I would like to continue to do so by your side.
‪臣日后也想一直陪在您身边
It means, "The trees must be dense for there to be any to axe."
‪树木茂盛之处便会招致斧头砍伐
"And the shades must be dark for the birds to fly in."
‪树荫浓密 鸟禽才会前来栖息
DAEHAKJANGGU
‪（《大学章句》）
Now, tell me…
‪现在告诉我吧
what your answer
‪关于我的提议
to my offer is.
‪你的答复是什么
Could you accompany me somewhere? It won't take long.
‪请随臣到一个地方
Do you remember?
‪您还记得吗？
This was the first place we came to after I became your lecturer.
‪这里是邸下上了我的书筵后 ‪初次和我一起来的地方
For some reason, that day feels like so long ago.
‪总觉得那天似乎是很久远的往事了
For once at least,
‪但至少您
can't you put your trust in others?
‪能试着去相信一次 不是吗？
Not for anyone else, but for yourself.
‪不是为了其他人 而是为了自身
For Your Royal Highness.
‪为了邸下您自己
Don't distance yourself too much.
‪不要过分和他人保持距离
It'll only make you lonelier.
‪那样会让您更加孤单
I swore to myself I would never come back to the palace.
‪臣曾经发誓不再进宫
If I hadn't, I would have regretted it.
‪但若真是如此 我应该会后悔莫及
The truth is, I'm not the type to stay in one place for too long.
‪坦白说 依臣的性情 ‪无法在同个地方停留太久
So I plan to go back to the way
‪所以我打算重新回到
I used to live.
‪我原先的生活方式
I hope you will be happy…
‪臣希望您能得到幸福
not just for a day,
‪并不是只有一天
but every day.
‪而是每天都能幸福
Because when I had no dreams or hopes,
‪因为替毫无梦想和希望的我
you brought happiness to my life.
‪带来幸福的人正是邸下
I don't think I can accept
‪臣无法接受
a different position as you suggested
‪您将我另调他职的命令
because if I stay,
‪因为只要待在宫中
I will keep coming to your quarters.
‪我就会不断跑到东宫殿探头探脑
I might use saying hello to the royal tutors as an excuse.
‪我可能会以 ‪要和侍讲院师长们问候为由
Or I might use the beautiful tree at your quarters as an excuse too.
‪或者拿东宫殿的树木很美当借口
If not those,
‪否则就是
I might pretend to look for Lord Jaeun at your quarters
‪假装来看者隐君大监是否来访
when who I really want to find is you.
‪心中却期待能够见到您
NOTICE OF RESIGNATION
‪（辞职䟽）
Please stay healthy, Your Royal Highness.
‪请您保重 邸下
I hope you won't be lonely.
‪请不要感到孤单
NOTICE OF RESIGNATION
‪（辞职䟽）
How has it been for you? I thought you might be feeling lonely.
‪你还好吗？ ‪我想你心里可能会感到空虚
Not at all.
‪怎么会呢？
The Crown Prince is well, right?
‪邸下过得很好吧？
-Jan-i! -Is everything all right?
‪-潺怡 ‪-没什么事吧？
Why did you kill her? She didn't do anything wrong! Why?
‪你为何杀了她？她又没有做错什么！
You were able to hold yourself back until now.
‪您一直以来不是都好好忍住了吗？
But how come you couldn't this time?
‪但这次为何做不到？
I had to hold back for the last ten years.
‪我过去十年都忍下来了
The Crown Prince is responsible for the death of his uncle.
‪让世子邸下为叔父之死负责
Please dethrone the Crown Prince!
‪请废黜世子！
-Please dethrone him! -If you are dethroned,
‪-请废黜世子！ ‪-一旦遭到废黜
the only thing that awaits you would be death.
‪等着你的就只有死路一条
I will protect you, Your Royal Highness.
‪我会守护邸下的